when people ask me if a food is healthy
or not my response is
compared to what
so when studies show
cheese has a neutral or beneficial
effect on health that's the question i
sought to answer
[Music]
in a series of videos i did about
saturated fat i talked about a major
campaign launched by the global dairy
industry to neutralize the negative
image of milk fat among regulators and
health professionals as related to heart
disease that campaign continues to this
day with the publication of a
meta-analysis demonstrating neutral
meaning non-harmful associations between
dairy products and cardiovascular
disease and death
okay well first of all how do we know
the dairy industry had anything to do
with this study well
it was published in a journal that
forces authors to disclose financial
conflicts of interest let's see
what they divulged
dairy dairy dairy dairy dairy dairy the
fourth largest dairy company in the
world dairy dairy milk beer soda
mcdonald's dairy dairy dairy dairy dairy
oh and the study itself was explicitly
funded by
dairy dairy dairy
okay then
the other big new one was this
suggesting that a little bit of cheese
every day isn't just neutral but
actually good for you
and they make it clear that they have no
conflicts of interest they're just
employees of the yeli innovation center
and the yelly r d center you know
china's largest dairy producer
making it one of the world's largest
dairy companies
okay but how can cheese consumption be
associated with better health outcomes
well most of these studies were from
europe where cheese consumption is
associated with a higher socioeconomic
status see in europe they're not eating
cheese whiz and velveeta cheese is
generally an expensive product and so
who eats cheese those with higher paying
jobs higher socioeconomic strata higher
education levels all of which are
associated with better health outcomes
which may have nothing to do with their
cheese consumption
higher socioeconomic groups also consume
more fruits and vegetables and more
candies so i bet you could do a
population study and show candy
consumption is associated with better
health
don't tell the national confectioners
association
too late did you know that candy
consumers have lower levels of
inflammation a 14
decreased risk of elevated blood
pressure brought to you by the candy
industry and the usda our government
which props up the sugar industry to the
tune of a billion dollars a year
it's like when our tax dollars are used
to buy up surplus cheese paul shapiro
wrote a great editorial imagine the
headline government buys 20 million in
surplus pepsi or hard-earned tax dollars
buying up millions of unwanted cola cans
all as a favor to the flailing soda
industry which just kept producing
drinks no one wanted as outrageous as
such a government handout to the soda
industry would be that's exactly what
the usda is doing for the dairy industry
michelle simon did a great report on how
our government colludes with the
industry to promote dairy junk foods the
federal government administers checkoff
programs to promote milk and dairy
mcdonald's has six dedicated dairy
checkoff program employees at its
corporate headquarters to try to squeeze
in more cheese that's how we got double
steak quesadillas
that's how we got three cheese stuffed
crust pizza complete with a summer of
cheese
these funds are being used to promote
foods that contribute to the very
diseases our federal government is
allegedly trying to prevent
does it make sense to tell americans to
avoid foods high in salt sugar and
saturated fat while engaging in the
promotion of those same foods
look the meat and dairy industries can
do what they like with their own money
but the public power of taxation should
be used for the public good not to
support the dairy and candy industries
when industry-funded studies
suggest their products have neutral
health effects
or even beneficial
one question you always have to ask is
compared to what is cheese healthy
compared to what and if you're sitting
down to make a sandwich cheese is
probably healthy compared to bologna but
compared to peanut butter no way that's
the point walt willett made a former
chair of nutrition at harvard to
conclude that dairy foods aren't neutral
could be misleading as it could be
misinterpreted to mean that increasing
consumption of dairy foods would have no
effects on cardiovascular disease or
mortality
loss is that the health effects of
increasing or decreasing consumption of
dairy foods would depend importantly on
the specific foods that are substituted
for dairy foods like what are you going
to put on your salad cheese would be
healthy
compared to bacon but not compared to
nuts
see consumption of nuts or plant protein
has been found to be protectively
associated with the risk of coronary
heart disease and type 2 diabetes in
contrast intake of red meat for example
has been associated with increased risk
thus it's reasonable to assume that the
lack of association with dairy foods
could put them somewhere in the middle
of a spectrum of healthfulness
but certainly not an optimal source of
energy or protein
more broadly the available evidence
supports policies that limit dairy
production and encourages production of
healthier sources of proteins and fats
he wasn't just speculating this was
based on three famous harvard studies
involving hundreds of thousands of men
and women exceeding five million person
years of follow-up
this was really the first large scale
prospective study to examine dairy fat
intake compared to other types of fat in
relation to heart attack and stroke risk
so replacing like 100 calories of fat
worth of cheese 100 calories a fat worth
of peanut butter on a daily basis might
reduce risk up to 24
where a substitution with other animal
fats might make things worse
here's how it breaks down for heart
disease swapping dairy fat for like
vegetable oil would be associated with a
decrease in disease risk where swapping
dairy for meat
increases risk
dairy fat calories may be as bad or
worse as straight sugar
the lowest risk would entail swapping to
a whole plant food like whole grains
yeah dairy products are a major
contributor to the saturated fat in the
diet have thus been targeted as one of
the main dietary causes of
you know the number one killer of men
and women
but the dairy industry likes to argue
there are other things in dairy products
like fermentation byproducts and cheese
that could counteract the saturated fat
effects
all part of an explicit campaign by the
dairy industry to neutralize the
negative image of milk fat among
regulators and health professionals
if
global dairy platform looks familiar
they were one of the funders of the milk
and dairy's neutral study trotting out
their dairy fat is counteracted notion
to which the american heart association
responds that no information from
controlled studies supports the
assertion that fermentation adds
beneficial nutrients to cheese that
somehow counteract the harmful effects
of the saturated fat we need to cut down
on dairy meat coconut oil no matter what
their respective industries say
in fact that's the reason the american
heart association felt they needed to
release this special presidential
advisory in 2017 they wanted to set the
record straight on why well
well-conducted scientific research
overwhelmingly supports limiting
saturated fat in the diet
[Music]
so
you